Guide to the Dane Rudhyar Papers, 1922-1973
Department of Special Collections
Dane Rudhyar Papers,
1922-1973
Special Collections M0264
Rudhyar, Dane, 1895-
.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Dane Rudhyar, 1974-1976.
Biographical Note
Composer, author, and painter. Born 1895 in Paris, France and emigrated to the United States in 1916. He wrote orchestral works, piano and compositions, and works on cosmopsychology.
Scope and Content
Manuscripts of musical compositions, correspondence (1924-1973): Aaron Copeland, Henry Cowell, Carlos Chavez, Martha Graham, Carl Ruggles, and Edgar Varese, and one concert program.
Container List
- 1. The Seed Center, Winter-Spring. Printed brochure advertising Rudhyar poetry books and others. (Folder 1.)
- 2. Carlos Salzedo. 1 page carbon copy typescript recommendation for Guggenheim Memorial Fellowship. n.d.
- 3. 1973, May 7.Leo Ornstein to D.R. LS, Brownsville, Texas. Cello sonata, Lysistrata suite, Seller's tape., 1 p.
- 4. N.D.,n.p. Roy Harris to D.R. ALS, 2 pp.
- 5. 1931, Oct 19.Eugene Goossens to D.R. T.L.S., Cincinnati, with D.R. note attached., 1 p.
- 6. N.D.Henry Cowell to D.R., N.Y., 1 1/2 pp.
- 7. 1929, Sep 9.Martha Graham to D.R., 3 pp.
- 8. 1928, Jul 18.Carl Ruggles to D.R. ALS, Arlington, Vt., 2 pp.
- 9. -, Nov 26.Carl Ruggles to D.R., ALS, Arlington, Vt., 4 pp.
- 10. 1926, Dec 6Carl Ruggles to D.R., ALS, Arlington, Vt., 8 pp.
- 11. N.D.Carl Ruggles to D.R. ANS, n.p., 2 pp.
- 12. N.D.Carl Ruggles to D.R. ALS, St. Petersburg, Florida, 3pp.
- 13. 1924, Sept 25.[L. Stokowski] Boris to D.R. TLS Philadelphia D.R. note attached., 1 p.
- 14. 1924, Oct 18.[L. Stokowski] Boris to D.R. TLS, Philadelphia, 1 p.
- 15. 1937, Aug 11.F.H. Price, Free Library of Philadelphia to D.R. TLS. Edwin A. Fleisher Music Collection., 2 pp.
- 16. 1938, Nov 16.D.R. to F.H. Price. TL (carbon unsigned). Hollywood.
- 17. [1958?]Leo Ornstein to D.R. ALS [N.Y.] D.R. note attached., 3 pp.
- 18. 1926, Sep 21.Roy Harris to D.R. ALS and cover. Paris, France., 3 pp.
- 19. 1949, Feb 11.Francisco Curt Lange to D.R. TLS, 1 p.
- 20. 1926, Nov 8.Carl [Ruggles] to D.R. APcS Arlington, Vt.
- 21. N.D.Carl [Ruggles] to D.R. ALS n.p., 3 pp.
- 22. 1928, March 15.Carlos Chavez to D.R. ALS, 2 pp.
- 23. 1928, March 6Carlos Chavez to D.R. ALS N.Y., 2. pp.
- 24. ?, Jun 13.A(aron) Copland to D.R. ALS Santa Fe, 1 p.
- 25. [ca 1922]Henry Cowell to D.R. ANS on printed announcement of Carl Ruggles' Whitney Studio Club talks. N.Y., 4 pp.
- 26. [1921]Henry Cowell to D.R. A.Pc.S.
- 27. 1954, Oct. 2.Henry [Cowell] to D.R. ALS n.p., 1 p.
- 28. 1921,Christmas. Henry Cowell to D.R. ANS on signed musical inscription n.p., (Two sides of slip).
- 29. 1946, Jan 10.Henry Cowell to D.R. TLS, Fresno, CA, 1.p.
- 30. N.D.Henry Cowell to D.R. ALS, N.Y., 1 p. With autographed musical inscription on verso.
- 31. 1924, Jul 20.(Edgar) VArese (1883-1965) to D.R. ALS in French. N.Y., 1 p.
- 32. 1927, Dec 12.(Edgar) Varese to D.R. ALS in French, N.Y., 2 pp.
- 33. (1928, Feb 22)Edgar Varese to D.R. ALS in French, N.Y., 2 pp.
- 34. (1928), Mar 7.D.R. to Varese. T.L. (carbon) Hollywood, 2 pp.
- 35. 1928, Mar 7.Edgar Varese to D.R. ALS in French. N.p., 2 pp.
- 36. N.D. (June?)E(dgar) V(arese) to D.R. ALS in English, N.Y., 1 p.
- 37. 1946, Aug 18.(Edgar) Varese to D.R. ALS in English, n.p., 1 p.
- 38. N.D.Louise Varese (1890-1989) to D.R. ANS on card, (N.Y.), 1 p.
- 39. N.D.Carl (Ruggles) to D.R., n.p., ALS, 2 pp. Re Schoenberg.
- 40. 1950, Mar 11.Program for Composer's forum in cooperation with the New York Public library. Includes Rudhyar's Moments and Ouranos.
- Pentagram No. 1: The Summons for the piano. Composer's ms., transparencies., Title + 11 leaves numbered 2-12. (Folder 2.)
- Pentagram No. 2: Enfoldment for the piano. Composer's ms., transparencies., Title + 9 leaves numbered 2-10.
- Pentagram No. 3: Release for the piano. Composer's ms., transpariencies., Title + 10 leaves numbered 2-11.
- Pentagram No. 4: The Human Way for the piano. Composer's ms., transparencies., Title + 16 numbered leaves.
- Fanfares: Adolescence (To the North)
  - Composer's ms. p. [1-2] of 4, with [Fanfares] Rebirth (to the Zenith)
  - Composer's ms. p. [3-4] of 4, 2 leaves ms. music untitled.
- Primavera; Tetragram No. 8
  - Composer's ms. 8 pp.:cover p[2-6] music p. [7-8] blank.
- Tetragrams (Third Series) No. 8: Primavera
  - Composer's ms., 6 numbered leaves.
  - Perforation for spiral binding at left.
- Tetragram 7: Tendrils
  - Composer's ms., One leaf designated p. 6-7.
- Part of Summer Nights
  - Composer's ms., 1 leaf designated p. 6-7.
- The Way of Power, from Pentagram
  - (2) Yearning (for piano), 3 pp.
  - Composer's ms. p. 4-6.
  - (3) Irony
  - Composer's ms. p. 44-45, (2 pp.)
  - (5) Place
  - Composer's ms. p. 46-48, (3 pp.)
- Syntony, in 4 movements for the piano. (Folder 3.)
  - Composer's ms. Cover.
  - 1. Dithyramb 20 unnumbered pages:
    [1, title; 2, blank; 3-3, music; 14, blank; 15, music sketch, with diagonal red strike out line; 16, blank; 17, music sketch, with diagonal red strike out line; 18-20, blank]
  - 2. Eclogue, 4 unnumbered pages [1, title, 2-4 music].
  - 3. Prophetic Rite
    - Early version, 1935., 8 numbered pages: 1-6, music; 7-8, blank.
  - 4. Apotheosis
    - Oct 31, 1924, 5 unnumbered pages.
- (1) Transcription by Rudhyar of Hymne a la Vie by F. Nietzsche 2 pp. ms. (Folder 4.)
- (2) 1924 Oct.Ruggles, Carl; Men & Mountains symphonic ensemble published by New Music, Arlington, Vermont., 24 pp.
- (3) 1924Ruggles, Carl: Lilacs from Men & Mountains ms., 2 pp.
  - Inscribed to Rudhyar, 1926, Nov.
    Note: transcribed by Dane Rudhyar 1925.
- (4) [N.D.][Ruggles, Carl] - One leaf music sketch with notes, 2 pp.
- (5) 1929Euphoria by Henry Cowell 1 p. for Blanche Walton.